So a few years ago,
منذ بضع سنوات،
I did something really brave,
قمت بعمل شجاع بالفعل،
or some would say really stupid.
مع أن البعض قد يعتبره أمرا غبيا حقا.
I ran for Congress.
ترشحت للكونغرس.
For years, I had existed safely behind the scenes in politics
لسنوات، كنت موجودة بأمان خلف الكواليس فيما يخص السياسة
as a fundraiser, as an organizer,
كجامعة تبرعات وكمنظمة
but in my heart, I always wanted to run.
ولكن بداخلي، لطالما أردت أن أترشح.
The sitting congresswoman had been in my district since 1992.
كانت ممثلة الكونغرس متواجدة بدائرتي الانتخابية منذ عام 1992.
She had never lost a race,
لم تخسر أي سباق أبدا،
and no one had really even run against her in a Democratic primary.
ولم يقم أي أحد حتى بالترشح ضدها في انتخابات الحزب الديمقراطي.
But in my mind, this was my way
و لكن في ذهني، كانت هذه هي طريقتي
to make a difference,
لإحداث فرق،
to disrupt the status quo.
لإرباك الوضع الراهن.
The polls, however, told a very different story.
ومع ذلك، فإن صناديق الاقتراع روت قصة مختلفة تماما.
My pollsters told me that I was crazy to run,
أخبرتني استطلاعات الرأي خاصتي أن ترشحي فكرة مجنونة،
that there was no way that I could win.
أن فوزي غير ممكن بأية طريقة.
But I ran anyway,
لكنني ترشحت رغم ذلك،
and in 2012, I became an upstart in a New York City congressional race.
وفي عام 2012، قمت بقفزة في سباق الكونغرس في مدينة نيويورك.
I swore I was going to win.
أقسمت بأنني سأفوز.
I had the endorsement from the New York Daily News,
كانت تؤيدني صحيفة نيويورك دايلي نيوز،
the Wall Street Journal snapped pictures of me on election day,
التقطت جريدة وول ستريت صورا لي في يوم الانتخابات،
and CNBC called it one of the hottest races in the country.
وأطلقت عليه CNBC واحدا من أهم السباقات في البلاد.
I raised money from everyone I knew,
جمعت المال من كل الأشخاص الذين أعرفهم.
including Indian aunties
بما فيهم خالات هنديات.
that were just so happy an Indian girl was running.
اللاتي كن سعيدات جدا لأن فتاة هندية قد ترشحت.
But on election day, the polls were right,
لكن في يوم الانتخابات، كانت الاستفتاءات محقة،
and I only got 19 percent of the vote,
وحصلتُ على نسبة 19 بالمئة فقط من الأصوات،
and the same papers that said I was a rising political star
ونفس الصحف التي قالت أنني نجمة سياسية صاعدة
now said I wasted 1.3 million dollars
صرحت الآن أنني هدرت ما قدره 1.3 مليون دولار
on 6,321 votes.
على 6321 صوتا.
Don't do the math.
لا تقوموا بأي حسابات.
It was humiliating.
لقد كان الأمر محرجا.
Now, before you get the wrong idea,
قبل أن تأخذوا فكرة مغلوطة.
this is not a talk about the importance of failure.
هذه المحادثة ليست عن أهمية الفشل.
Nor is it about leaning in.
ولا عن المثابرة.
I tell you the story of how I ran for Congress
أروي لكم قصة ترشحي للكونغرس
because I was 33 years old
لأنني كنت بعمر 33 سنة
and it was the first time in my entire life
وكانت تلك أول مرة في حياتي
that I had done something that was truly brave,
قمت فيها بشيء شجاع بالفعل،
where I didn't worry about being perfect.
حيث أنني لم أقلق بشأن كوني مثالية.
And I'm not alone:
ولست الوحيدة:
so many women I talk to tell me
الكثير ممن أتحدث إليهن من النساء يخبرنني
that they gravitate towards careers and professions
أنهن ينجذبن إلى الوظائف والمهن
that they know they're going to be great in,
التي يعلمن أنهن سيتميزن فيها،
that they know they're going to be perfect in,
أنهن سيكن مثاليات فيها،
and it's no wonder why.
ولاعجب في ذلك.
Most girls are taught to avoid risk and failure.
لأنه يتم تدريس معظم الفتيات لتجنب المخاطر والفشل.
We're taught to smile pretty,
يتم تعليمنا أن نبتسم بشكل جميل،
play it safe, get all A's.
أن نلعب بطريقة آمنة، وأن نحصل على درجات ممتازة.
Boys, on the other hand,
الأولاد، من ناحية أخرى،
are taught to play rough, swing high,
يتم تعليمهم اللعب بخشونة والتأرجح عاليا،
crawl to the top of the monkey bars and then just jump off headfirst.
الزحف إلى أعلى القضبان الأفقية والقفز بعد ذلك على رؤوسهم.
And by the time they're adults,
وبحلول الوقت الذي يصبحون فيه بالغين،
whether they're negotiating a raise or even asking someone out on a date,
سواء أكانوا يتفاوضون حول زيادة في الراتب أو مجرد سؤالهم شخصا ما لمرافقتهم في موعد،
they're habituated to take risk after risk.
فإنهم اعتادوا على المخاطرة مرارا وتكرارا.
They're rewarded for it.
وتتم مكافأتهم على ذلك.
It's often said in Silicon Valley,
ويقال كثيرا في وادي السيليكون،
no one even takes you seriously unless you've had two failed start-ups.
أن لا أحد يأخذك على محمل الجد إلا بعد فشل شركتين ناشئتين من صنعك.
In other words,
بعبارة أخرى،
we're raising our girls to be perfect,
نحن نربي بناتنا ليكن مثاليات،
and we're raising our boys to be brave.
ونربي أولادنا ليكونوا شجعانا.
Some people worry about our federal deficit,
بعض الناس يشعرون بالقلق حول العجز في الميزانية الفدرالية لدينا،
but I, I worry about our bravery deficit.
لكنني أقلق بشأن عجز الشجاعة لدينا.
Our economy, our society, we're just losing out
اقتصادنا ومجتمعنا، نحن نخسر فقط
because we're not raising our girls to be brave.
لأننا لا نربي فتياتنا ليكن شجاعات.
The bravery deficit is why women are underrepresented in STEM,
عجز الشجاعة هو سبب ضعف تمثيل المرأة في STEM،
in C-suites, in boardrooms, in Congress,
في ألقاب الشركات وفي مجالس الإدارة وفي الكونغرس،
and pretty much everywhere you look.
وإلى حد كبير أينما نظرتم.
In the 1980s, psychologist Carol Dweck
في الثمانينات، قامت عالمة النفس كارول دويك
looked at how bright fifth graders handled an assignment
بالنظر إلى مدى ذكاء تعامل طلاب الصف الخامس مع واجب ما
that was too difficult for them.
والذي كان صعبا جدا بالنسبة لهم.
She found that bright girls were quick to give up.
فوجدت أن الفتيات الذكيات كن أسرع في الاستسلام.
The higher the IQ, the more likely they were to give up.
كلما زاد معدل ذكائهن، كلما رجحت نسبة استسلامهن.
Bright boys, on the other hand,
الأولاد الأذكياء، من ناحية أخرى،
found the difficult material to be a challenge.
وجدوا في صعوبة المادة تحديا.
They found it energizing.
وجدوا فيها منشطا.
They were more likely to redouble their efforts.
كانوا أكثر قابلية لمضاعفة جهودهم.
What's going on?
ما الذي يحدث؟
Well, at the fifth grade level,
حسنا، على مستوى الصف الخامس،
girls routinely outperform boys in every subject,
تتفوق الفتيات بشكل روتيني على الأولاد في كل مادة،
including math and science,
بما في ذلك الرياضيات والعلوم،
so it's not a question of ability.
إذن هذه ليست مسألة قدرة.
The difference is in how boys and girls approach a challenge.
الفرق هو في كيفية مقاربة الأولاد والفتيات لتَحَدٍّ ما.
And it doesn't just end in fifth grade.
وهذا لا ينتهي في الصف الخامس فقط.
An HP report found that men will apply for a job
وجد تقرير لHP أن الرجال سيتقدمون بطلب عمل
if they meet only 60 percent of the qualifications,
إذا كانوا يُلَبون 60 في المئة فقط من المؤهلات،
but women, women will apply
ولكن النساء، النساء ستيقدمن
only if they meet 100 percent of the qualifications.
فقط إذا كن حققن 100 في المئة من المؤهلات.
100 percent.
100 في المئة.
This study is usually invoked as evidence that, well,
عادة ما يتم ذكر هذه الدراسة كدليل على أن، حسنا،
women need a little more confidence.
المرأة تحتاج إلى المزيد من الثقة .
But I think it's evidence
ولكنني أعتقد أنها دليل
that women have been socialized to aspire to perfection,
على أن النساء تمت برمجتهن اجتماعيا للتطلع إلى الكمال،
and they're overly cautious.
وهن حذرات للغاية.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And even when we're ambitious,
وحتى عندما نكون طموحات،
even when we're leaning in,
حتى عندما نثابر،
that socialization of perfection
فإن تلك التنشئة الاجتماعية من الكمال
has caused us to take less risks in our careers.
قد كانت سببا في اتخاذنا مخاطر أقل في عملنا.
And so those 600,000 jobs that are open right now
إذن فالوظائف 600000 الشاغرة في الوقت الراهن
in computing and tech,
في الحوسبة والتكنولوجيا،
women are being left behind,
يتم ترك النساء في الخلف،
and it means our economy is being left behind
وهذا يعني أن اقتصادنا يتراجع للوراء
on all the innovation and problems women would solve
على مستوى جميع الابتكارات والمشاكل التي كانت ستحلها النساء
if they were socialized to be brave
إذا ما تم إنشائهن اجتماعيا على أن يكن شجاعات
instead of socialized to be perfect.
عوض أن يتم إنشائهن اجتماعيا على أن يكن مثاليات.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So in 2012, I started a company to teach girls to code,
إذن وفي عام 2012، بدأتُ شركة لتعليم البرمجة للفتيات،
and what I found is that by teaching them to code
وما اكتشفته هو أنه ومن من خلال تعليمهن البرمجة،
I had socialized them to be brave.
كنت قد برمجتهن اجتماعيا على أن يكن شجاعات.
Coding, it's an endless process of trial and error,
البرمجة، هي عملية لا نهاية لها من التجربة والخطأ،
of trying to get the right command in the right place,
في محاولة للحصول على الأمر المناسب في المكان الصحيح،
with sometimes just a semicolon
مع وفي بعض الأحيان مجرد فاصلة منقوطة
making the difference between success and failure.
لخلق الفرق بين النجاح والفشل.
Code breaks and then it falls apart,
ُيفصل رمز ومن ثم ينهار،
and it often takes many, many tries
وعادة ما يستغرق الأمر الكثير والكثير من المحاولات
until that magical moment
حتى تلك اللحظة السحرية
when what you're trying to build comes to life.
عندما يتحقق ماكنت تحاول بناءه .
It requires perseverance.
يتطلب الأمر مثابرة.
It requires imperfection.
يتطلب الأمر نقصا.
We immediately see in our program
نحن نرى على الفور في برنامجنا
our girls' fear of not getting it right,
خوف فتياتنا من "عدم إنجاز الأمر بطريقة صحيحة،
of not being perfect.
من أن لا يكن كاملات.
Every Girls Who Code teacher tells me the same story.
تخبرني كل مُدرِّسة في برنامج فتيات مُبرمِجات القصة ذاتها.
During the first week, when the girls are learning how to code,
خلال الأسبوع الأول، أثناء تعلم الفتيات للبرمجة،
a student will call her over and she'll say,
سوف تناديها إحدى الطالبات وتقول لها،
"I don't know what code to write."
"أنا لا أعرف أي رمز أكتب."
The teacher will look at her screen,
ستنظر المدرّسة إلى شاشتها،
and she'll see a blank text editor.
وسوف ترى محرر نص فارغ.
If she didn't know any better, she'd think that her student
لو لم تكن على دراية بالوضع، لظنت أن تلميذتها
spent the past 20 minutes just staring at the screen.
أمضت ال 20 دقيقة الماضية وهي تحدق في الشاشة فقط.
But if she presses undo a few times,
ولكن إذا ضغطت على زر الرجوع عدة مرات،
she'll see that her student wrote code and then deleted it.
سوف ترى أن تلميذتها كتبت الرمز ثم حذفته.
She tried, she came close,
لقد حاولت، وكانت على وشك إيجاده،
but she didn't get it exactly right.
ولكنها لم تصل إلى الحل بالضبط.
Instead of showing the progress that she made,
بدلا من إظهار التقدم الذي أنجزته،
she'd rather show nothing at all.
فهي تفضل عدم الإدلاء بأي شيء على الإطلاق.
Perfection or bust.
الكمال أو الإخفاق.
It turns out that our girls are really good at coding,
لقد اتضح أن فتياتنا جيدات حقا في الترميز،
but it's not enough just to teach them to code.
ولكن هذا لا يكفي لتعليمهن كيفية الترميز.
My friend Lev Brie, who is a professor at the University of Columbia
صديقي ليف بري، وهو أستاذ في جامعة كولومبيا،
and teaches intro to Java
ويدرس مقدمة لجافا
tells me about his office hours with computer science students.
يحكي لي عن ساعات عمله بالمكتب مع طلاب علوم الكمبيوتر.
When the guys are struggling with an assignment,
عندما يكون الأولاد في صراع مع واجب ما،
they'll come in and they'll say,
فإنهم سوف يأتون وسيقولون،
"Professor, there's something wrong with my code."
"أستاذ، هناك خطب ما بترميزي."
The girls will come in and say,
في حين أن الفتيات يذهبن إليه ويقلن:
"Professor, there's something wrong with me."
"أستاذ، إن بي خطبا ما."
We have to begin to undo the socialization of perfection,
علينا أن نبدأ في التراجع عن التنشئة الاجتماعية بهدف الكمال،
but we've got to combine it with building a sisterhood
ولكن علينا أن نجمعها مع بناء جماعة من الأخوات
that lets girls know that they are not alone.
تتيح للفتيات معرفة أنهن لسن وحيدات.
Because trying harder is not going to fix a broken system.
لأن بذل جهد أكبر لن يصلح نظاما معطلا.
I can't tell you how many women tell me,
لا أستطيع إخباركم كم من امرأة تقول لي،
"I'm afraid to raise my hand,
"أنا أخشى رفع يدي،
I'm afraid to ask a question,
أنا أخشى طرح سؤال ما،
because I don't want to be the only one
لأنني لا أريد أن أكون الوحيدة
who doesn't understand,
التي لا تفهم،
the only one who is struggling.
الوحيدة التي تعاني."
When we teach girls to be brave
عندما نعلم الفتيات أن يكن شجاعات
and we have a supportive network cheering them on,
ونمتلك شبكة داعمة لتشجيعهن،
they will build incredible things,
فسوف يقمن ببناء أشياء لا تصدق،
and I see this every day.
وأنا أرى هذا كل يوم.
Take, for instance, two of our high school students
فلنأخذ على سبيل المثال، اثنتين من طالبات الثانوية لدينا
who built a game called Tampon Run --
اللتين قامتا ببناء لعبة تسمى "تامبون ران" -
yes, Tampon Run --
نعم، "جرية السدادة القطنية" -
to fight against the menstruation taboo
لمحاربة تابو الحيض
and sexism in gaming.
والتمييز على أساس الجنس في الألعاب.
Or the Syrian refugee
أو اللاجئة السورية
who dared show her love for her new country
التي تجرأت بإظهار حبها لبلدها الجديد
by building an app to help Americans get to the polls.
من خلال بناء تطبيق لمساعدة الأمريكيين للوصول إلى صناديق الاقتراع.
Or a 16-year-old girl who built an algorithm
أو فتاة تبلغ من العمر 16 عاما والتي بنت خوارزمية
to help detect whether a cancer is benign or malignant
للمساعدة في الكشف عن ما إذا كان السرطان حميدا أو خبيثا
in the off chance that she can save her daddy's life
في أمل ضعيف منها بإنقاذ حياة والدها
because he has cancer.
لأنه مصاب بالسرطان.
These are just three examples of thousands,
هذه ليست سوى ثلاثة أمثلة لآلاف
thousands of girls who have been socialized to be imperfect,
من الفتيات اللواتي تمت تنشئتهن اجتماعيا ليكن غير كاملات،
who have learned to keep trying, who have learned perseverance.
اللواتي تعلَّمن الاستمرار في المحاولة، واللواتي تعلَّمن المثابرة.
And whether they become coders
وسواء أصبحن مبرمجات
or the next Hillary Clinton or Beyoncé,
أو هيلاري كلينتون التالية أو بيونسيه،
they will not defer their dreams.
فإنهن لن يأجلن أحلامهن.
And those dreams have never been more important for our country.
وتلك الأحلام لم تكن أبدا أكثر أهمية بالنسبة لبلادنا.
For the American economy, for any economy to grow,
في سبيل أن يكون الاقتصاد الأمريكي، أي اقتصاد ناميا،
to truly innovate,
ولكي نبدع حقا،
we cannot leave behind half our population.
لا يمكننا تجاوز نصف سكاننا.
We have to socialize our girls to be comfortable with imperfection,
يجب علينا أن ننشئ بناتنا ليكن مرتاحات مع عدم الكمال،
and we've got to do it now.
وعلينا أن نفعل ذلك الآن.
We cannot wait for them to learn how to be brave like I did
لا يمكننا أن ننتظر منهن أن يتعلمن كيف تكن شجاعات كما فعلت أنا
when I was 33 years old.
عندما كان عمري 33 عاما.
We have to teach them to be brave in schools
علينا تعليمهن أن يكن شجاعات في المدارس
and early in their careers,
وفي وقت مبكر من حياتهن المهنية،
when it has the most potential to impact their lives
عندما يكون لذلك قدرة أكثر للتأثير على حياتهن
and the lives of others,
وحياة الآخرين،
and we have to show them that they will be loved and accepted
وعلينا أن نظهر لهن أنهن سوف يكن محبوبات ومقبولات
not for being perfect
لا لكونهن مثاليات
but for being courageous.
ولكن لكونهن شجاعات.
And so I need each of you to tell every young woman you know --
ولذا فإنني أحتاج من كل واحد منكم أن يقول لكل امرأة شابة يعرفها -
your sister, your niece, your employee, your colleague --
أختك، ابنة أختك، موظفتك الخاصة، زميلتك -
to be comfortable with imperfection,
أن تكون مرتاحة في عدم الكمال،
because when we teach girls to be imperfect,
لأنه وعندما نعلم الفتيات أن يكن غير مثاليات،
and we help them leverage it,
ونساعدهن على تطوير ذلك ،
we will build a movement of young women who are brave
عندها سوف نبني حركة شابات شجعات
and who will build a better world for themselves
واللواتي سوف يبنين عالما أفضل لأنفسهن
and for each and every one of us.
ولكل واحد منا.
Thank you.
شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Chris Anderson: Reshma, thank you.
كريس أندرسون: ريشما، شكرا لكِ.
It's such a powerful vision you have. You have a vision.
إنك تمتلكين رؤية قوية جدا. لديكِ رؤية.
Tell me how it's going.
أخبريني كيف تسير الأمور.
How many girls are involved now in your program?
كم عدد الفتيات المشاركات حاليا في برنامجكِ؟
Reshma Saujani: Yeah. So in 2012, we taught 20 girls.
ريشما سوجاني: نعم. حسنا في عام 2012، درَّسنا 20 فتاة.
This year we'll teach 40,000 in all 50 states.
هذه السنة سوف ندرس 40000 في جميع الولايات ال 50.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And that number is really powerful,
وهذا العدد قوي حقا،
because last year we only graduated 7,500 women in computer science.
لأنه وفي العام الماضي تخرجت لدينا 7500 امرأة فقط في علوم الكمبيوتر.
Like, the problem is so bad
إن المشكلة سيئة للغاية
that we can make that type of change quickly.
بحيث جعلتنا نقوم بهذا النوع من التغيير بسرعة.
CA: And you're working with some of the companies in this room even,
ك.أ: وأنتم تشتغلون مع شركات بعضها موجود في هذه الغرفة
who are welcoming graduates from your program?
ممن يرحبون بخرِّيجات البرنامج؟
RS: Yeah, we have about 80 partners,
ر.س: نعم، لدينا حوالي 80 شريكا،
from Twitter to Facebook
من تويتر لفيسبوك
to Adobe to IBM to Microsoft to Pixar to Disney,
لأدوبي لشركة آي بي إم لمايكروسوفت لبيكسار لديزني،
I mean, every single company out there.
يعني كل شركة متواجدة.
And if you're not signed up, I'm going to find you,
وإذا لم تكن من المنخرطين فسأجدك ،
because we need every single tech company
لأننا بحاجة إلى كل شركة من شركات التكنولوجيا
to embed a Girls Who Code classroom in their office.
لتضمين أحد الفصول الدراسية لبرنامج فتيات مُبرمِجات في مكاتبهم.
CA: And you have some stories back from some of those companies
ك.أ: ولديك قصص من بعض تلك الشركات
that when you mix in more gender balance
أنه وعند الاختلاط المتوازن بين الجنسين
in the engineering teams, good things happen.
في فرق الهندسة تحدث أمور جيدة .
RS: Great things happen.
ر.س: تحدث أشياء عظيمة.
I mean, I think that it's crazy to me to think about the fact
أنا أعني ، أنه ومن الجنون بالنسبة لي التفكير في حقيقة
that right now 85 percent of all consumer purchases are made by women.
أنه وحاليا 85 في المئة من جميع المشتريات الاستهلاكية مصنوعة من قبل النساء.
Women use social media at a rate of 600 percent more than men.
تستخدم النساء وسائل الإعلام الاجتماعية بنسبة 600 في المئة أكثر من الرجال.
We own the Internet,
نحن نملك شبكة الإنترنت،
and we should be building the companies of tomorrow.
ويجب علينا بناء شركات الغد.
And I think when companies have diverse teams,
و أعتقد أنه وعندما تعين الشركات فرقا متنوعة،
and they have incredible women that are part of their engineering teams,
وهم يملتكون نساء رائعات كجزء من فرق الهندسة خاصتهم،
they build awesome things, and we see it every day.
إنهن يبنين أشياء مذهلة، ونحن نرى ذلك كل يوم.
CA: Reshma, you saw the reaction there. You're doing incredibly important work.
ك.أ: ريشما، لقد رأيت رد الفعل هناك. أنت تقومين بعمل مهم للغاية.
This whole community is cheering you on. More power to you. Thank you.
هذه الجماعة كلها تهتف لكِ . المزيد من القوة لكِ. شكرا.
RS: Thank you.
ر.س: شكرا لك. (تصفيق)